Suriya Kumar



Career Objective

Experienced professional with **4+ years** of experience. Have gained good exposure to understand various aspects of **Data Science** through the certification which has developed a great sense of confidence at a very personal level. Hence, I seek a technically challenging position in the area of **Data Analytics, Data Science, Business Analysis & related fields** where I can share my skills & expand my capabilities further in the pursuit of progressive career advancement.



Experience

Nov 2020 present

Python Developer : Neoware, Chennai

- Developed Covid 19 Tracking project with Flask and Plotly and developed within short span
 of time.
- Currently doing PubMed project with inclusive of JavaScript and jQuery for client side.
- Discuss technical and design issues with other developers ,managers, users or customers whenever necessary to achieve best solution.
- Helped recruit and grow development talent. Experience building REST APIs.
- Extensive knowledge of how web semantics translate into a REST API.
- Experience programming and delivering in a production environment.
- Expertise working with data structures and algorithms.
- Proficiency in object-oriented programming and experience applying modern design patterns.

Sep 2019 -Oct 2020

Full Stack Developer : NIC, Chennai

- PHP, Html5, Javascript, Jquery, Json, Ajax, Bootstrap 4 and Object oriented Programming language.
- · Worked in District and Town panchayat project with PHP and Angular
- Currently working in Tax project- Water tax, Profession and Property tax
- Effectively develop and collaborate with others to develop, Database- centric solutions within a distributed team of SQL / PostgreSql
- Develop technical system documentation.

Mar 2017 -Nov 2019

Data Analyst : Winsoft Technologies, Chennai

- Successfully interpreted data to draw conclusion for managerial action and strategy
- Analyzed statistical interpreted data for managerial action & strategy
- Presented finding and data to team to improve strategies and operations
- Proposed solutions to improve system efficient and reduce total expenses.

Sep 2015 -Nov 2016

Lecturer : Srinivasa Engineering College, Dharmapuri



Projects

Data Science with R: Health Care Cost Analysis

- Recorded the patient statistics, the agency wants to find the age category of people who frequently visits the hospital and found maximum expenditure.
- Performed complete analysis on variable and factor affects the hospital costs

Data science With Python : Comcast Consumer Compliant

- Created a heatmap for the no. of complaints Monthly & daily granularity levels & found frequency for those values.
- Analyzed & sorted which state has maximum complaints & highest frequency of unsolved complaints.

Advanced Machine Learning : Mercedes-Benz Greener Manufacturing

- Performed data wrangling and prepared the data for further analysis.
- Applied label encoding for categorical features. Performed dimensionality reduction.
- Used XGBoost machine learning algorithm to predict the results

Tableau : Retail Sales Performance Analysis

 Built a dashboard that will present monthly sales performance by product segment & category to help client identifying them.

Big Data Hadoop & Spark : Stock Exchange Data Analysis

- Automated the training process & predict the next days win or loses.
- Did Exploratory Data Analysis. Analyzed how MoM or YoY companies from different segment or industries.



Address

Chennai-60042, Tamil Nadu, India

Phone

+91-9965661965,+91-7339456076

E-mail

ksuriyaramani@gmail.com

LinkedIn

linkedin.com/in/suriya-kumar-05b374a2/



Certifications

Master's Program - Data Scientist :

Simplilearn Certified in collaboration with IBM

- Data Science with Python, R
- Advance Machine Learning
- Tableau 10
- Big Data Hadoop & Spark Developer

Certified Web Development: Zuan Education

In-Plant Training

• HCL Carrier Development Center, Chennai



Education

B.E.: Electronics &

Communication

Annamalai University | Percentage : 72.4%

HSC

Venus Matriculation Higher Secondary School, State Board | Percentage : 83.7%

X (Matric)

Venus matriculation Higher Secondary School, Matriculation | Percentage : 89.3%



Technical Skills

PHP, HTML, CSS, JS, jQuery, Ajax



SQL, PostgreSql, Angular, Bootstrap 4



Machine Learning

••••

Data Science with Python, R

••••

Data Visualization: Tableau 10

••••

Big Data Hadoop & Spark





Achievements

- Second Prize for the Research Paper "Car Speed Controller Using Bluetooth Technology", surge'15, Department of Electrical Engineering, Annamalai University, Annamalai Nagar.
- Awarded Best Student of Co-curricular Activities for the year 2014-2015.